<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Electronics on Bits &amp; pieces - Sven Wehrend</title>
    <link>http://wehrend.uber.space/tags/electronics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Electronics on Bits &amp; pieces - Sven Wehrend</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://wehrend.uber.space/tags/electronics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reducing Rare Earth Dependence: The Quest for Alternative Magnetic Materials</title>
      <link>http://wehrend.uber.space/posts/web/20_reducing_rare_earth_elements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://wehrend.uber.space/posts/web/20_reducing_rare_earth_elements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;sect2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;_introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rare earth elements have long been the backbone of high-tech magnets, with metals like neodymium and dysprosium playing&#xA;pivotal roles in various industries. However, the scarcity and rising demand for these valuable resources have prompted&#xA;researchers to seek alternative solutions. In an effort to reduce our reliance on rare earth magnets, scientists are&#xA;exploring innovative materials and alloy combinations.&#xA;Among the promising contenders is cerium, an abundant and accessible rare earth element, showing potential to replace&#xA;or augment neodymium magnets. In this article, we’ll delve into the groundbreaking research by Thomas Lograsso and his&#xA;team at the Ames Laboratory of the US Department of Energy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking the Secrets of Rare Earth Elements: The Remarkable Case of Neodymium</title>
      <link>http://wehrend.uber.space/posts/web/19_rare_earth_elements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://wehrend.uber.space/posts/web/19_rare_earth_elements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;sect2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;_introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rare earth elements, often shrouded in mystery, play a crucial role in our modern world. From smartphones&#xA;to electric vehicles, renewable energy technologies, and even defense systems, these elements are the unsung&#xA;heroes that make our daily lives more sustainable, efficient, and connected. In this article, we’ll delve&#xA;into the fascinating world of rare earth elements, with a focus on the versatile element, neodymium.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;sect2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;_the_rare_earth_elements_an_overview&#34;&gt;The Rare Earth Elements: An Overview&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rare earth elements (REEs) are a group of seventeen chemical elements that occupy the lanthanide series of the periodic&#xA;table, along with scandium and yttrium. Despite the name, they are not necessarily rare, but they are typically found in&#xA;low concentrations, making their extraction and purification challenging and costly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Op-Amps introduction</title>
      <link>http://wehrend.uber.space/posts/web/18_op-amps_introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://wehrend.uber.space/posts/web/18_op-amps_introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;sect1&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;_op_amp&#34;&gt;OP-Amp&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;sectionbody&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today I want to speak about op-amps. These wonderful, but mysterious components, we have heavely often appearing&#xA;in circuit schematica of analog or analog / digital hybrid circuits. We want to demistify these components.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../op-amp.svg&#34; alt=&#34;op-amp&#34; width=&#34;400px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are two basic thumb rules when handling ideal op-amp circuit. (Real-world op-amp circuits are a bit more complicated, but we will discuss this later).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph image&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;title&#34;&gt;1. The first thumb rule is that Vout is essentially the difference of the voltage values at the both inputs, multiplied with an arbitrary but high amplification factor A.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
